<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
To change this license header, choose License Headers in Project Properties.
To change this template file, choose Tools | Templates
and open the template in the editor.
-->

<article>
  <headline>FAQs: What’s a GCQ bubble?</headline>
  <source>By:<writer> Gabriel Pabico Lalu </writer> - Reporter / <email>@GabrielLaluINQ </email></source>
  <pubDate><underline>INQUIRER.net </underline> / 12:02 AM March 22, 2021</pubDate>
   
    <aBody>
        <para>
		MANILA, Philippines — A lot of questions have cropped up regarding the general community quarantine (GCQ) bubble 
		that will be enforced in Metro Manila, Bulacan, Cavite, Laguna, and Rizal from March 22 to April 4.
	</para>

	<para>
		INQUIRER.net answers some of those questions based on the resolution issued by the Inter-Agency Task Force on 
		Emerging Infectious Diseases (IATF) and the information that presidential spokesperson Harry Roque gave in a press 
		briefing on Sunday.
	</para>
	
	<para>
		<bold>What is a <italic> bubble </italic>?  What does that mean for travel? </bold>
	</para>	

	<para>
		A bubble is an area where entry and exit are restricted—except during emergencies. Adopted by different sports 
		organizations, like the National Basketball Association in the United States, people entering the bubble are 
		tested for COVID-19 to prevent infection in the area. In other words, a bubble is aimed at preventing infected 
		people from getting in or getting out.
	</para>
	
	<para>
		So travel to and from the bubble —  in this case, composed of Metro Manila, Bulacan, Cavite, Laguna, and Rizal — 
		will not be allowed unless deemed essential.
	</para>
	
	<para>
		<bold>Who will be allowed to go in and out of the <italic>bubble </italic>? And for what purposes?</bold>
	</para>	
	
	<para>
		Those allowed to get in and out of the bubble are authorized persons outside their residences (APORs), 
		which include the following:
		
		<bullet>essential workers with valid identification cards</bullet>
		<bullet>health and emergency frontline service personnel</bullet>
		<bullet>government officials</bullet>
		<bullet>accredited humanitarian assistance workers</bullet>
		<bullet>persons traveling for humanitarian reasons</bullet>
		<bullet>persons going for travel abroad</bullet>
		<bullet>persons crossing zones for work or business or going back home</bullet>
		<bullet>returning overseas Filipinos and overseas Filipino workers </bullet>	
		
		If you live within the bubble and work outside of it, or vice versa — for example, if you work in Metro Manila 
		and living in Pampanga — you will be granted access provided that you bring supporting documents. If you are a 
		tourist outside of the bubble and will be returning to your home inside the bubble, you will also be allowed to 
		get in as long as you provide documents stating where you reside.
	</para>
    </aBody>
</article>
